Guide to the French Revolution and Napoleonic Period Manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
French Revolution and Napoleonic Period Manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
- Autograph manuscripts
  - Les-Mol (Box 10)
    - Marmontel, Jean-Francois, 1765; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 39)
      Receipt in French, and a portrait
    - Masséna, General, to Senator Garat, 12 sept. 1801; 1 leaf + 8 leaves (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - Mathilde Bonaparte, Princess, to ?, n.d.; 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 10, Folder 41)
      ALS in French, plus portraits and biographical notice
    - Miremont, to M. le Maire de Vienne, 22 Aug. 1808; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 42)
      ALS in French, on the local tin mines, endoresed by the Sous-Préfet du Rhône
    - Mauger, to a Conseiller d'Etat, 15 May 1806; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 43)
    - Maure, Nicolas-Sylvestre [People's Representative in the Dpts of Seine-et-Marne and Yonne], 15 Febr. 1794; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 10, Folder 44)
      ALS in French: descriptive list of about 250 people kept in jail in the Department of Seine-et-Marne ["marchand de grain", "ex-noble", "parent d'émigré", "domestique d'émigré", "ex-chanoine", "curé", aristocrate prononcé", "ex-constituant", "suspect d'incivisme", "pour avoir dit qu'il signerait le procès-verbal des assemblées primaire avec sa canne", etc.] with partial translation
    - Menou, Jacques, 17 Jan. 1794; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 45)
    - Merlin de Douai, Philippe-Antoine, to the Minister of Finance, 1798; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 46)
    - Merlin de Douai, Philippe-Antoine, to Camille Desmoulins, 17 Jan. 1790; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 47)
      ALS in French, with translation: asks D. to insert two announcements in his journal
    - Milet de Mureau,[Préfet of the Corrèze], to the Minister of Finance, 14 Mrch 1803; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 48)
    - Milet de Mureau [Préfet of the Corrèze], to Thouin [Curator at the Musée d'Histoire naturelle], n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 49)
    - Miollis, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 50)
    - Mirabeau, Honoré Gabriel Riqueti, Comte de, to the Baron de Maltzan, 4 Aug. 1770; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 8 leaves (Box 10, Folder 51)
      ALS in French to Maltzan, to whom M.owned money; plus translation, plus portraits and notes
    - Moeune, to Ducloz, 1793; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 52)
    - Molitor, Gabriel, to Gen. Lecourbe, 5 Oct. 1797; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 53)
    - Mollien, Nicolas, to Mme Michel, 1812; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 54a)
    - Mollien, Nicolas, to Baron Bignon*, 7 March 1838; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 54b)
      ALS in French: congratulations about Bignon's "Histoire de France sous Napoleon" (10 vols. 1829-1838)
  - Mon-Pef (Box 11)
    - Monge, Gaspard, to the Administrateurs des Postes, 18 Oct. 1793; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Montalivet, Jean-Pierre de [Minister of the Interior], to Honoré Joseph Antoine Ganteaume, Préfet maritime de Toulon*, 4 January 1810; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 2a)
      ALS in French about some "graines qui sont parvenues de Vienne a Paris" for the Botanic Museum in Toulon
    - Montalivet, Jean-Pierre de [Minister of the Interior], to the Préfet d'Erfurt, 16 Nov. 1811; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 2b)
    - Montalivet, Jean-Pierre de [Minister of the Interior]*, 15 May 1815; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 2c)
      ALS in French [draft]: pension of 20,000 francs for la duchesse de Frioul
    - Montbrun, General, to a Commissaire-Ordonnateur, 23 Oct. 1812; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 3)
      [Figueras, Spain] ALS in French, plus translation and biographical notes
    - Montesquiou-Fezensac, François Xavier Marc Antoine, to Baron Bouvier, 26 oct. 1814; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Monthion, General de, to Berthier, 10 Aug. 1811; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Montholon, General de, to Duclos, 31 May 1853; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Montjoie, Christophe Félix Louis Ventre de la Touloubre, sometimes called Garlart de, to Dupuy, 21 Sept. 1793; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 8)
      ALS in French and Italian, with transcription/translation
    - Montmorency-Laval, to M. Lavalette, 29 May 1808; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Moreau [?], 1802; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 10)
      ALS in French: bill for horse food
    - Morgan, Jacques Polycarpe, to another general, 21 Aug. 1806; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 11)
      ALS in French, plus biographical notice
    - Mortier, general Edouard, to the Minister of War, 11 april 1803; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Mouchy, Marshall Duke of, to the Marshall Duke of Richelieu, 3 may 1783; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Mouton, General, to Soult, 1831; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Muy, General du, or Dumuy, to Mme de Simiane, 30 april 1802; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 15)
      [Bourges] ALS in French, containing a paragraph about General Menou, a.k.a. Abdullah Jacques-François de Boussay de Menou, who had converted to Islam while serving in Egypt with Dumuy: "My colleague Menou has permitted me once to be in the same appartment with his wife, but she was dressed in a severe oriental costume and Mahomet fell upon her eyes, with a veil making her impenetrable"
    - Napoléon Bonaparte [?], 29 Aug. 1798; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Napoléon Bonaparte, Consul [endorsement], 24 March 1800; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 17)
      ALS in French: military assignation, also signed by Berthier, Minister of War, and General Andréossy
    - Napoleon Bonaparte, Consul, 24 Dec. 1799; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 18)
      ALS in French: decoration ["fusil d'honneur"] awarded to Louis Lecompte for his bravery in Verona, Italy, also sigend by Maret and Berthier
    - Napoléon Bonaparte, Consul [in the name of], 7 Febr. 1803; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 19)
      ALS in French: nomination of an extractor in the Tribunal of Dieckirch or Diekirch, then in the French Department of Forêts [in present Belgium, Luxembourg and Germany], signed by Régnier
    - Napoléon Bonaparte, Consul, 2 July 1803; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 20)
      ALS in French [COPY]: appointment of a diplomat, plus twelve portraits of Talleyrand
    - Napoléon Bonaparte, Consul, 4 June 1804; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 21)
      ALS in French: Brevet de sous-lieutenant for J.J. Laminck
    - Napoléon Bonaparte, Ex-Emperor [fake copy], 1821?; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 22)
      ALS in French: copy of his testament
    - Necker, Jacques, to? [ the Bureau de la Ville?], 2 Sept. 1789; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 23)
      [Versailles] ALS in French, plus a translation: on the purchase of one thousand sacks of flour which, though having been reported to be very bad, were sent to Mr. Thierry, baker in Versailles. Necker [?] orders further examination. Authenticity is difficult to establish.
    - Nesselrode, Charles Robert, Comte, to ?, 13 May 1816; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 24)
      [Paris] ALS in French, with an autograph annotation by A.D.White on the back: "This autograph was given to me in 1855 while I was attached to the Am[erican] legation at St. Petersburg - just after my interview with the old statesman, who in his day played with great inspiration the part of jackal to the lion Metternich. A.D. White,Cornell University, Sept. 14th 1882."
    - Ney, Marshall, to Mr. Bresson [de Valensole], 26 Sept. 1814; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 25)
      ALS in French, with autograph endorsements of three other Marshalls of France [Davout, Mortier and Suchet]. Ney requests his agent to proceed at once to Vienna (Austria), where the Congress had just assembled and would open on November 1., and to take the necessary steps to ensure the continuance of his dotations or, at least, the equivalent in revenues. His fellow-marshalls agree to a similar arrangement.
    - Noailles, Louis Marie, Vicomte de, [Philadelphia], n.d. [1797?]; 1 leaf + 12 leaves (Box 11, Folder 26)
      ALS in English, plus notes
    - Orléans, Louis Philippe, Duc d', to the Comte de Vernon, Dec. 1785; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 27)
      ALS in French: about the death of his father
    - Orléans, Marie-Adélaïde, to "M. Roi, ministre des Finances" [in fact, Antoine Roy], 30 Oct. 1820; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 11, Folder 28)
      ALS in French, plus translation and graphics [portraits and pictures of the family chapel at Dreux]
    - Otto, Louis Guillaume, Comte de Mosloy, to Bank Perregaux [or Perrégaux] and Cie, 10 June 1805; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Oudinot, Nicolas Charles, to another General, 7 June 1801; 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - Pache, Jean Nicolas, to the Attorney General-Syndic of Paris, 27 Sept. 1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Pache, Jean Nicolas, to Citizen Paul [Mayor of Toulon], 8 Oct. 1792; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Pache, Jean Nicolas, to ?, 28 Nov. 1793; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Paganel, Pierre, to the Minister of War, 12 Oct. 1797; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Palloy, Pierre-François, to Coetreles, 4 Sept. 1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 11, Folder 35)
      ALS in French, plus translation, plus portrait, plus notice
    - Palloy, Pierre-François, to ?, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Palloy, Pierre-François, to Charles-Philippe Ronsin, 3 Febr. 1794; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - Panis, Etienne-Jean, to mme Duplessis (Camille Desmoulins's Mother-in-law), August 1794; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - Paré, Jules, to the Minister of War, 24 Jan. 1794; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - Paris. Administration du Département, to the Minister of Finance, 20 Jan. 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 40)
    - Paris, Maire de, 18 July 1790; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 41)
      ALS in French, signed by Capitaine Murray of the garde Nationale
    - Paris. Commune, Assemblée des Représentants, August 1789; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 42)
    - Paris. Comité Permanent des Représentants de la Commune, 4 dec. 1789; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 43)
    - Paris. Conseil Général de la Commune [list of the members of], 29 March 1791; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 44)
      ALS in French, with 74 signatures/144 members, notably Cousin, Garran de Coulon, Grouvelle, Cretet, Quatremère de Quincy, etc.
    - Paris, Commune de, Police Department, 14 Sept. 1792; 1 leaf + 11 leaves (Box 11, Folder 45)
      ALS in French, with seal of the municipality, plus notes
    - Paris, Commune de, Police Department, 22 July 1793; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 46)
      ALS in French: on the transfer to the Prison de l'Abbaye of General Custine
    - Paris, Commune, Section [subunit] des Piques, 3 June 1793; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 47)
      ALS in French: on Citizen Lennequin, former priest
    - Paris, Commune, Section [subunit] des Tuileries, 25 Sept. 1792; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 48)
      ALS in French, on Citizen Pollin
    - Paris, Commune, Section [subunit] Poissonière, 3 July 1794; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 49)
      ALS in French, on Citizen Moisson
    - Paris, Commune, Section [subunit] de l'Indivisibilité, 22 Jan. 1794; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 50)
      ALS in French, on monetary compensation voted to the Committee members
    - Paris, Commune, Section [subunit] des Sans-Culottes, 17 July 1794; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 51)
      ALS in French, on female suspects
    - Parlement de Paris, [5 Aug. 1789]; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 52)
      Document in French, Facsimile
    - Parlement de Bordeaux, [24 Nov. 1789]; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 53)
    - Parlement de Normandie, [25 June 1788]; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 54)
    - Parlement de Navarre (Pau), [17 July 1788]; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 55)
    - Parlement de Paris, siégeant a Troyes, [27 Aug. 1787]; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 56)
    - Parlement de Paris, [4 May 1788]; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 57)
    - Parlement de Paris, [7 May 1788]; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 58)
    - Parlement de Paris, [13 Sept. 1788]; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 59)
    - Pau, Citizens of, 1788; 3 leaves (Box 11, Folder 60)
      ALS in French, Facsimile
    - Pelet de la Lozère, Jean, to tghe Minister of Finance, n.d. [after 1830]; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 61)
    - Pelletier or Peltier [?], Ingénieur des Mines, 1788; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 62)
      Manuscript in French
    - Penières-Delzors, Jean-Augustin, to ?, n.d. [1795]; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 63)
    - Pérignon, General, n.d.; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 64)
      ALS in Italian, plus a portrait
    - Perregaux (or Perrégaux), Jean-Frédéric, to M. Gorneaux, 7 dec. 1789; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 65)
    - Perrin, General, to General de Laviolais, 15 oct. 1799; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 66)
    - Pertusier, Charles, n.d.; 28 leaves (Box 11, Folder 67)
      Photocopies and translations [poems, letters to Bernardin de Saint-Pierre]
  - Pet-R (Box 12)
    - Petiet, Claude, to the Minister of War, 5 Dec. 1799; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Pétion de Villeneuve, Jérôme, to ?, 5 May 1792; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Pétion de Villeneuve, Jérôme, to Palloy, 6 July 1792; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Petitguillaume, General, to a Commissaire-Ordonnateur en Chef, 28 Oct. 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 4)
      ALS in French, on the supply of food and ustensils for troups, plus translation
    - Pichegru, General Charles, to General Pille, 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Pichegru, General Charles, to General Taponnier, 16 Nov. 1795; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Pichegru, General Charles, to General Vernier, 1796; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Pille, General, to the Minister of War, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Piombino, Elisa Bonaparte-Bacciochi, Future Duchesse de, 5 Dec. 1799; 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 12, Folder 9)
      ALS in French, also signed by Felix Bacciochi, plus portraits of her
    - Piorry, Pierre, Biography of, Jan. 1816; 4 leaves + 8 leaves (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Polignac, Jules de, to M. Fayau, Argentier des Ecuries du Comte d'Artois, 3 May 1787; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Polignac, Melchior de, n.d. [c. 1820]; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Pommereul, Préfet du Département d'Indre-et-Loire, to Fontenai [or Fontenay], 6 Jan. 1802; 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Poniatowski, Prince Józef Antoni, to Joseph Nowosulski, Surgeon in the Polish Army, [Warsaw], 18 Febr. 1808; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 14)
      ALS in Polish, with a printed seal of the Grand-Duchy of Warsaw, plus translation
    - Pontécoulant, Louis Gustave Doulcet-, to the Minister of Finance, 10 febr. 1806; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Portalis, Joseph Marie*, n.d. [1803]; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 16a)
      Notes in French: draft manuscript concerning the divorce in the Civil Code (Titre VI, chapitre 2, "Des formes du divorce") with corrections in Portalis's hand.
    - Portalis, Joseph Marie, to the Préfet des Deux-Sèvres*, 13 February 1807; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 16b)
      ALS in French about a payment due to a curate in Assay.
    - Portalis, Joseph Marie, to M. de Fontenay, [Florence] 14 June 1818; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 16c)
    - Poussielgue, Jean-Baptiste, to ?, 17 Aug. 1795; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Pozzo di Borgo, Carlo, to M. Erskine, 1. April 1804; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 18)
      ALS in French, plus partial translation [document partly torn]
    - Pradel, Commissaire-Ordonnateur, to Citizen Pary, 1795; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Pradt, Dominique, Abbé de, to General Baudran, 11 april 1832; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Prieur de la Marne, Pierre-Louis, and General Turreau, to general Marceau, 18 Oct. 1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Prudhomme, Louis, to the Minister of Finance, 4 Jan. 1793; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Pully, Comte de, to Brissot the younger, 20 Aug. 1813; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Quenault, du Conseil d'Etat, to M. le Grand (Ministry of Finance), 1803; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Quinette, Nicolas Marie, to the Préfet of Deux-Sèvres, 10 Jan. 1811; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Ramel-Nogaret, Dominique Vincent, to Gaudin, Commissaire du Directoire, 19 Oct. 1798; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Rampon, General-Senator, to M. Perregeaux, 13 Febr. 1805; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Randon, Marshall Jacques Louis, to Captain Milson, 5 Jan. 1867; 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Réal, Pierre, to M. Mouchet, 20 May 1811; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - Réant, Quartermaster-Treasurer of the Consular Guard, to Citizen Lefebvre, 7 Sept. 1803; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - Regnault de Saint Jean d'Angély, Michel-Louis-Étienne, to the Minister of Finance, 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - Regnault de Saint Jean d'Angély, Michel-Louis-Étienne, to M.Beauchamp, 14 Oct. 1801; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 32a)
    - Regnault de Saint Jean d'Angély, Michel-Louis-Étienne, to M. de Montlosier *, 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 32b)
    - Regnault de Saint Jean d'Angély, Michel-Louis-Étienne, to the Minister of Finance, 24 Dec. 1802; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Regnault de Saint Jean d'Angély, Michel-Louis-Étienne, to Councillot of State Frochot, 19 June 1804; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 34)
      ALS in French, on a commission of three Councillors of State entrusted to visit the Paris prisons and investigating possible improvements, plus translation
    - Régnier, Claude, to the Minister of War*, 6 May 1801; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 35a)
      ALS in French, with the printed seal of the Ministry of Justice, about the situation of customs officers drafted into military service
    - Régnier, Claude, to the Minister of War*, 2 December 1804; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 35b)
      ALS in French, about radiations from the "liste des émigrés", and the restoration of some property
    - Régnier, Claude, to the Préfet Maritime de Toulon, 1804; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 35c)
      ALS in French, with the printed seal of the Ministry of Justice, plus translation
    - Reille, General, to a Notary, n.d.; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 36)
    - Reinhard, Karl Friedrich, to Treilhard, 23 Jan. 1798; 1 leaf + 1 leaf +2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 37)
      ALS in French, plus a second letter to the same, plus notes
    - Reubell, Jean Francois, to Rudler, Commissaire du Gouvernement, 4 March 1797; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 38)
      ALS in French, bearing the signatures of Reubell and Lagarde, Secretary General of the Directory, plus a portrait of Reubell
    - Reynier, to the People's Representatives to the North Army, 18 June 1795; 1 leaf +4 leaves (Box 12, Folder 39)
    - Richard, Joseph, to the People's Representatives to the North Army, 12 May 1795; 1 leaf +2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 40)
    - Richelieu, Armand Emmanuel Vignerot du Plessis, Duc de, to Vincent de Vaublanc, c. 1815; 1 leaf +2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 41)
      ALS in French. Documents the "White Terror" (July 1815-September 1816), during which royalist militia exacted retribution against Jacobins and the "traitors" who had rallied around Napoleon. Moderates like Richelieu opposed the civil war tactics of ultra-conservatives like Viomésnil (mentioned here), a veteran of the Revolutionary Army in America turned general in the counter-revolutionary armies in Europe, who was pushed to retire with the rank of Marshal in 1816.
    - Ricord, to "the Rédacteur des Annales politiques, Morales et Littéraires", 14 Oct. 1818; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 42)
    - Ris, Clément de, to Defermon, 12 March 1803; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 43)
    - Ris, Clément de, to Defermon, 1 July 1803; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - Rivière, Marquis de, to Major Way, 1795; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 45)
    - Roberjot, Claude, to ?, 1797; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 46)
    - Robert, François (Lieutnant in the Army of Sambre-et-Meuse), May 1795; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 12, Folder 47)
      ALS in French: petition for discharge and pension, plus translation
    - Rochambeau, Donatien Marie Joseph, Vicomte de, to Citizen Damez, May 1795; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 48)
      ALS in French, plus translation [N.B: doc. is defective]
    - Rochambeau, Donatien Marie Joseph, Vicomte de, to the Minister of War, 1793; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 49)
    - Rochambeau, Donatien Marie Joseph, Vicomte de, 1793; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 50)
      ALS in French: certifixcate for a leave of absence in teh Army, plus translation
    - Roger-Ducos, July 1795; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 51)
    - Roger-Ducos, to Defermon, 1802; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 52)
    - Roland de la Platière Jean-Marie, 13 Sept. 1792; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 12, Folder 53)
      ALS in French: order for military supply, plus translation
    - Roland de la Platière Jean-Marie, to the Syndic of Paris, 28 Sept. 1792; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 12, Folder 54)
    - Roland de la Platière Jean-Marie, to teh Adminsitrator of the Dpt. of Deux-Sèvres, 1793; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 55)
    - Roland de la Platière Marie-Jeanne, "Madame Rolland", to Henri Gosse (Geneva), [Lyon] 1 Febr. 1790; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 56)
    - Rondelet, Commission des Travaux Publics, 17 Sept. 1795; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 57)
      ALS in French: attestation
    - Rossignol, ex-General, to the Minister of War, 15 June 1800; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 58)
      ALS in French, on his being unable to find a means to join the army of Egypt
    - Rostollant, General, to the Director of Posts, 8 July 1800; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 59)
    - Rousseau, Claude Louis, Bishop of Coutances, to [Mgr. Fesch?], 14 october 1805; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 60)
    - Rouyer, Colonel Jean Victor, 1805; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 60)
    - Rovere de Fontvielle, Joseph, to the Minister of War, 1797; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 61)
  - S (Box 13)
    - Sablé, Bien-Aimé, [Brest] 28 Febr. 1815; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Saint-André, Jean-Bon to, [Brest] 21 april 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Saint-Hilaire, General louis-Joseph, to the Minister of War, 24 June 1803; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Saliceti, Antoine Christophe, to Amnbroise Francischetti [in Bastia], [Genova] 10 March 1804; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Santerre, Antoine Joseph, to Citizen Trimaille, 1792; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 6)
      ALS in French, with seal, plus translation
    - Santerre, Antoine Joseph, to Frochot, 11 Aug. 1792; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Sartine, 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Savary, Anne Jean Marie, to the Minister of War, 28 Dec. 1799; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 9a)
    - Savary, Anne Jean Marie, to Lavalette*, 14 May 1804; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 9b)
      ALS in French about the military police in Piemont
    - Savary, Anne Jean Marie, to "Messieurs les administrateurs de la Comptabilité nationale"*, 22 May 1806; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 9c)
      ALS in French (recommandation)
    - Savary, Anne Jean Marie, to a High-Ranking Civil Servant in the Ministry of Police, 7 May 1813; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 9d)
      ALS in French: Draft of a circular letter to the Prefects on the "spirit of opposition and disobedience in parts of the Empire... The principal basis of all the disorders is to be found in desertion. I cannot hide from His Majesty the fact that this condition of affairs is due to the weakness of the local administration... I wish to present a report which contains precise facts and statistics. I beg you, Monsieur, to be good enough to drawn up a table, according to the model attached, of the deserters and refractory cases which are found in your department."
    - Sherlock, Sauveur-Francois-Louis, to Lemercier, about his postulating for the Senate, July 1801; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 10a)
    - Schibli, Agent of the Population of Fislispach [near Baden, Germany] to General Paillard, 21 June 1799; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 10b)
      ALS in French, on requisitions imposed on the locals by the French military
    - Sébastiani, Minister of Foreign Affairs, 1. Aug. 1832; 1 leaf (Box 13, Folder 11)